Finding Aid for Gerald L. K. Smith Papers 1922-1976
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gerald L. K. Smith Papers 1922-1976
Smith, Gerald L. K. (Gerald Lyman Kenneth), 1898-
85818 Aa 2
Founder of the America First Party, head of the Christian Nationalist Crusade, and outspoken anti-Semite. Correspondence, speeches, oral history transcript, memoranda and other materials detailing his criticism of America's participation in World War II, his Michigan senatorial race in 1942, his campaign for the presidency in 1944, his opposition to the spread of communism after the war, and his support of conservative Christian causes and right wing individuals and organizations; and photographs. Portraits of Smith and his wife, Elna Smith; photographs of meetings and conventions of the America First Party, of picketing and other political activity in support of Smith and his platform, and of Smith's associates and supporters; also photographs and portraits of celebrities, buildings, and activities, which Smith collected, probably for use in his publication The Cross and the Flag.
102 linear feet
2 phonograph records
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The bulk of the Smith collection (Donor No. 1082 ) came to the library in March 1982 following the probating of Smith's will. Prior to that, the library had collected some of the published materials of Smith, an oral history interview, and a microfilm copy of a portion of the papers, filmed while still in Smith's custody.
The collection is open for research.
Gerald Lyman Kenneth Smith was born February 27, 1898 in Pardeeville, Wisconsin. Called to the ministry like his father, Lyman Z. Smith, and other members of his family before him, Smith attended Valparaiso University and Butler University in Indiana, and was then ordained a minister of the Disciples of Christ. In 1922, Smith married Elna Marion Sorenson, who came to be an active and important co-worker in the causes of her husband.
During his early ministry, Smith held pastorates in Indianapolis, Indiana and in Shreveport, Louisiana. While in Louisiana, Smith became a close friend and supporter of Governor and later U.S. Senator, Huey Long. A noted orator, Smith soon became a major spokesman for Long's "Share the Wealth" Program, and was called upon to conduct the funeral service for Long following his assassination in 1935. During the 1936 election campaign, Smith was associated with Father Coughlin and Francis Townsend in the work of the Union Party.
Even before election day, Smith had started to organize the Committee of 1,000,000, though it was not formally launched until March 1937. Formed as a nationalist front against the spread of communism, the Committee was isolationist, anti-union, and bitterly critical of the Roosevelt New Deal. In these years before World War II, Smith was searching for a base. He traveled about the country speaking whenever he could, and refining his image as a self-proclaimed crusader against communism and the C.I.O. In 1939, he began a series of broadcasts over WJR in Detroit, a powerful Midwestern station. Because of the receptiveness of this audience, some of whom were his larger financial backers, Smith decided to locate permanently in Detroit, moving there sometime that same year.
Smith worked with the Committee of 1,000,000 into the early 1940's. In April 1942, he published the first issue of the Cross and the Flag which came to be the principal means by which he spread his ideological message. Also in 1942, Smith ran unsuccessfully in the Republican primary for the United States Senate from Michigan. Undaunted by the returns, he ran as an independent in the fall election, but was again badly defeated.
In January 1943, Smith established the America First Party with the avowed purpose to provide an outlet for voters who might be dissatisfied with the candidates selected by the major parties in the 1944 national election. As Smith explained it, he hoped that his party would never have to go on the ballot, but since the Democrats and Republicans had already betrayed him and his followers in 1940 when they nominated "internationalists," he did not want them to be without recourse again. Smith did what he could to influence the choices of the major party conventions in 1944, but he was dissatisfied with Dewey and unalterably opposed to Roosevelt, so he felt compelled to run for president himself on the America First ticket.
After the war, about 1946, Smith formed the Christian Nationalist Crusade, a federation of over 60 right wing organizations, all with the purpose of fighting communism and upholding the ideals of "Christian Americanism." Smith was made national director of the CNC which was then headquartered in Detroit. In 1947, he moved his base of operation from Detroit to St. Louis. He himself then decided to live in Tulsa.
The Christian Nationalist Crusade, like most of Smith's other ideas, was based upon fear of a changing world and hatred of the supposed enemies of American and Christianity. Under the auspices of the CNC, Smith championed a variety of conservative and anti-communist causes. The CNC sponsored numerous meetings, distributed literature, organized petition campaigns, and lent their organizational skills to political candidates whose positions most resembled their own views. In 1952, Smith actively supported the candidacy of Douglas MacArthur for president. In the 1960's, he became a supporter of George Wallace.
Despite its St. Louis base, some of the most important activities and conventions of the CNC were centered in California, where Smith found some of his most influential backers. Thus, in 1953, Smith moved to Los Angeles, California. He and the CNC stayed there nearly twenty years, then moved to Eureka Springs, Arkansas. Smith devoted the final years of his life to a number of religiously-oriented projects. One was the management of a full-scale Passion Play presented each year in Eureka Springs. Another was the completion of a towering Christ of the Ozarks statue for which Smith had helped to raise the money. Other plans for Eureka Springs stalled with his death on April 15, 1976.
The Gerald L. K. Smith Papers are organized into ten series. The largest portion is in a chronological series with separate alphabetically arranged topical file for each year or range of years. There are a number of smaller subject series and series based on format of material including an audio-visual materials series with subseries of photographs, motion pictures and sound recordings.
Chronological files
1922-1938 [Box 1]
1939-1942 [Boxes 1-7]
1943 [Boxes 7-11]
1944 [Boxes 11-14]
1945 [Boxes 14-17]
1946 [Boxes 17-20]
1947 [Boxes 20-22]
1948 [Boxes 22-26]
1949 [Boxes 26-29]
1950 [Boxes 29-33]
1951 [Boxes 33-36]
1952 [Boxes 36-38]
1953 [Boxes 38-40]
1954 [Boxes 41-42]
1955 [Boxes 43-44]
1956 [Boxes 45-46]
1957 [Boxes 46-48]
1958 [Boxes 48-49]
1959 [Boxes 50-51]
1960 [Boxes 51-53]
1961 [Boxes 53-54]
1962 [Boxes 55-56]
1963 [Boxes 56-58]
1964 [Boxes 58-59]
1965 [Boxes 59-61]
1966 [Box 61]
1967 [Box 61]
1968 [Boxes 61-63]
1969 [Boxes 63-65]
1970 [Boxes 65-69]
1971 [Boxes 69-71]
1972 [Boxes 71-74]
1973 [Boxes 74-76]
1974 [Boxes 76-79]
1975 [Boxes 79-81]
1977 [Box 81]
Personal (scattered dates) [Box 81]
Administrative files [Boxes 82-90]
Loan file, 1969-1974 [Box 91]
Christian Nationalist Crusade
Newsletters [Boxes 92-93]
Oral History/Microfilm Project (and other MHC collected materials)
Transcripts of oral interviews, 1968 [Box 94]
Books and pamphlets published or distributed by the CNC [Box 95]
Microfilm of Smith collection [Box 96]
L. Z. Smith papers [Box 97]
United Farmers of America [Box 97-98]
Newsletters, pamphlets of other conservative individuals and groups [Box 99]
Audio-Visual Materials
Photographs [Box 100]
Motion Pictures [Boxes 101-102]
Sound recording discs [located in phonorecord collection]
The papers of Gerald L.K. Smith include correspondence, speeches, oral history transcript, memoranda and other materials detailing his criticism of America's participation in World War II, his Michigan senatorial race in 1942, his campaign for the presidency in 1944, his opposition to the spread of communism after the war, and his support of conservative Christian causes and right wing individuals and organizations; and photographs.
The major portion of the Gerald L.K. Smith papers came to the library in the spring of 1982. Before then, the library had accumulated a smaller group of Smith materials, mainly publications of the Christian Nationalist Crusade, mailings out of the Smith office from the 1960's and 1970's, the tapes and transcripts of an interview conducted with Smith in 1968 by a library staff member, and a few microfilm reels of a very small section of Smith's papers.
With the 1982 accession, the Smith collection now totals 102 linear feet of correspondence, memoranda, clippings, published materials, and photographs and motion pictures. The collection covers the years, 1922-1976, but bulks largest for the period since 1939. Regrettably, only scattered materials for the period before 1939 have survived so there is slight documentation of Smith's activities in Louisiana with Huey Long. What has survived from these years are a few letters from parents, some published sermons and radio speeches, and an assortment of notes, clippings, and meeting materials. It is perhaps surprising that not more of the collection had been discarded or mislaid. As the papers came from storage in Eureka Springs, Arkansas, the earlier files had been shifted about several times as Smith and his organization moved their base of operation: from Louisiana to Detroit, to St. Louis, to Los Angeles, and then to Eureka Springs. Smith seems to have been a careful record-keeper, however, and very little of the post-1939 files needed processing.
Subjects:
Antisemitism.; America First Party.; Christian Nationalist Crusade.; Christianity and antisemitism.; Clergy--United States.; Communism.; Conservatism.; Elections--Michigan--1944.; Judaism.; Oral history.; Presidents--United States--Election--1944.; Rightwing movements.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; World War, 1939-1945.; Christian Veterans of America.; Presidents--United States--Election--1948.; Presidents--United States--Election--1952.; Presidents--United States--Election--1956.; Presidents--United States--Election--1960.; Presidents--United States--Election--1964.; Bricker, John W. (John William), 1893-1986.; Eureka Springs (Ark.); MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.; McCarthy, Joseph, 1908-1957.; Smith, Gerald L. K. (Gerald Lyman Kenneth), 1898-1976; United Farmers of America.; Wallace, George C. (George Corley), 1919-1998.
Subjects - Visual Material
Afro-Americans--Civil rights.; America First Party.; Afro-Americans--Civil rights.; America First Party.; Evangelists.; Passion-plays.; Photographs.; Pickets.; Politics and government--1939-1945.; Politics and government--1946-1960.; Prejudice.; Revivals.; Riots.; Slogans.; Smith, Elna M.; Smith, Gerald L. K. (Gerald Lyman Kenneth), 1898-1976; Theatrical productions.; United States. Army Air Corps.; Wars.
Contributors:
Allen, Marilyn R.; Allstorm, Oliver.; Armstrong, George Washington, 1866-; Asher, Court.; Bealle, Morris A. (Morris Allison), 1891-1972; Beaty, John O. (John Owen), 1890-1961; Blake, Aldrich.; Britton, Frank.; Brown, Catherine.; Buckley, William F. (William Frank), Jr., 1925-2008.; Burke, Emory.; Carlson, John Roy.; Clark, Max A. X.; Close, Upton, 1894-1960; Comparet, Bertrand.; Stokes, Elizabeth Dilling, 1894-1966.; Doman, Bernard A.; Essig, Edith.; Fagan, Myron C. (Myron Coureval), b. 1887.; Fields, Edward R.; Fish, Hamilton, 1888-1991; Goff, Kenneth.; Gostick, Ron.; Green, G. F.; Hamilton, John W.; Hart, Merwin Kimball, 1881-1962.; Haushalter, Walter.; Hoffman, Clare Eugene, 1875-1967.; Hudson, Charles B.; Jaques, Norman.; Kister, Frederick.; Liebold, Ernest G., 1884-; Lohbeck, Donald, 1917-; Long, Earl Kemp, 1895-1960.; Loomis, Homer.; McAllister, Andrew B.; McClanahan, Meade.; MacFarland, W. Henry.; McGinley, Conde, d. 1963.; Maier, Walter Arthur, 1893-1950.; Marion, Leland L., 1895-; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956.; Moseley, George Van Horn, 1874-1960.; Mote, Carl Henry, 1884-1946.; Mullins, Eustace, 1923-2010; Murray, William Henry, 1869-1956.; Nasser, Gamal Abdel, 1918-1970.; National Blue Star Mothers of America.; Norris, J. Frank (John Frank), 1877-1952.; Nye, Gerald Prentice, 1892-1971.; Pegler, Westbrook, 1894-1969.; Pelley, William Dudley, 1890-1965; Perkins, Jonathon Ellsworth.; Reilly, Lawrence.; Reynolds, Robert Rice, 1884-1963.; Robertson, Charles.; Rockwell, George Lincoln, 1918-1967.; Romer, Harry, 1895-1953.; St.-George, Maximilian, b. 1885.; Schickedanz, Forrest.; Shuler, Robert Pierce, 1880-1966.; Smith, Elna M.; Smith, L. Z.; Sokolsky, George Ephraim, 1893-1962.; Southard, Earl.; Springer, Harvey H., 1907-1969; Stadsklev, C. O.; Stanley, David, Mrs.; Stoffel, Joseph H.; Swift, Wesley.; Tenney, Jack B.; Terminiello, Arthur W.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Vose, George.; Waybright, Edgar.; Welch, Robert.; Wheeler, Burton K. (Burton Kendall), 1882-1975.; White, Opal Tanner.; Winchell, Walter, 1897-1972.; Winegarner, Charles W.; Winrod, Gerald B. (Gerald Burton); Woodruff, Roy Orchard, 1876-1953.; Worrell, Margaret H.
- Chronological files
  The bulk of the Smith collection - the Chronological Series - has been arranged first by years, and then alphabetically within the year, so that except for the earlier years when groups of materials have been brought together, an alphabetical series exists for each year from 1943 to 1976. The amount of material for each year varies depending upon Smith's activities, but usually averages 3 to 4 linear feet. Inexplicably, the files for 1966 and 1967 are fragmentary, and may have been destroyed or mislaid. This series includes all types of materials, but consists primarily of correspondence. The file headings used are the names of individuals with whom Smith corresponded, organizations and issues in which he was interested, and places where Smith and his organization held meetings. There is also a miscellaneous folder for each letter of the alphabet.
  The subjects covered in the Chronological Series reflect Smith's own interests and activities. In general terms, the files concern the relationship between Smith and his ideological supporters, between Smith and his staff, attorneys, and those responsible for meeting arrangements and for the publication and distribution of the Cross and the Flag and other newsletters. Of special note are exchanges of letters between Smith and the many individuals who held contrary views.
  The Chronological Series is particularly valuable for information that it provides about the informal network and linkages among conservative organizations and individuals. Smith corresponded widely, and he and his staff collected material on the work of other conservatives, abroad as well as in the United States. Some of these individuals became closely associated with Smith and his work, speaking at his rallies or writing for the Cross and the Flag. Others started out with the Smith organization, then split off for ideological reasons or personal differences with Smith. Because Smith was a national figure, his files document conservative and anti-Zionist causes in many regions of the country and over a fairly broad period of time, 1940-1976. Correspondents and organizations represented in the collection include: George W. Armstrong (head of the Judge Armstrong Foundation for the furtherance of a unified anti-Semitic movement), John O. Beaty (university teacher and author of The Iron Curtain over America), Mrs. Catherine Brown (head of the National Blue Star Mothers of America), Elizabeth Dilling (anti-Communist crusader and director of the Patriotic Research Bureau), Myron C. Fagan (national director of the anti-Communist, Cinema Educational Guild), Kenneth Goff (pastor and head of various anti-Communist organizations in Colorado), Norman Jaques (Canadian M.P. and supporter of Smith and his work), Frederick Kister (director of the Christian Veterans of America), Conde McGinley (editor of anti-Communist newspaper, Common Sense), Leland Marion (pastor, and candidate for governor of Michigan in 1944 on the America First ticket), Jonathan E. Perkins (Los Angeles pastor and supporter of Smith), Harvey H. Springer (Colorado pastor and editor of Western Voice), Jack B. Tenney (California state senator and candidate for vice-president on the Christian National Party ticket in 1952), Rev. A. W. Terminiello ("Father Coughlin of the South," secretary of the Union of Christian Crusaders), Gerald P. Winrod (prominent pastor and publisher of Christian, anti Communist journal, The Defender).
  In addition, the Smith correspondence files contain letters from significant individuals who had no direct ties to Smith buy were responding to queries from Smith, or who were seeking Smith's advice. Smith sometimes initiated correspondence with individuals, either to castigate or compliment them, or just to spread his own views more broadly. Such correspondence is usually not extensive, but the letters are always of interest. Such correspondents include: H.L. Mencken, William F. Buckley, Gamal Abdul Nasser, Robert Welch, George Lincoln Rockwell, Westbrook Pegler, George Sokolsky, Arthur Vandenberg, and Ernest Liebold (secretary to Henry Ford).
  - 1922-1938
    - Correspondence (miscellaneous) 1922, 1932-1936 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with parents (hereafter filed under Smith)
      - 1922 (Box 1)
      - 1923 (Box 1)
      - 1924 (Box 1)
      - 1929 (Box 1)
    - Notices of meetings 1920s, 1930s (Box 1)
    - Lectures, "The Life of Christ" (Box 1)
      (14 parts; no. 11 missing)
    - Miscellaneous receipts, notes, etc., pre-1939 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings 1936 (Box 1)
    - Committee of 1,000,000 1937 (Box 1)
      (tickets to meetings)
  - Radio speeches 1932, 1938-1942
    (largely 1940-42)
    - A (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - America First (miscellaneous) circa 1940 (Box 1)
    - Anonymous (Box 1)
    - Applications
      - 1939 (Box 1)
      - 1940-1941 (Box 1)
    - Asman, Lorence (Box 1)
    - B (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - Bealle, Morris A. (Box 1)
    - Businessmen's form letter (Box 1)
    - C (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - Campaign materials 1942 (Box 1)
    - Canada (Box 1)
      (restriction of Cross and the Flag)
    - Citizens Keep America Out of War Committee (Box 1)
    - Cleveland meeting 1942 (Box 1)
    - Commentator magazine, Scribner's (Box 1)
    - Committee of 1,000,000
      - Detroit rally November 1939 (Box 1)
      - Erie, PA. rally April 1940 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous rallies: Lansing, Fort Wayne, Erie, Findlay, Grand Rapids (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - Tickets to meetings (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - January-March 1939 (Box 1)
      - April 1939 (Box 1)
      - May 1939 (Box 1)
      - June 1939 (Box 1)
      - July 1939 (Box 1)
      - August 1939 (Box 1)
      - September 1939 (Box 1)
      - October-December 1939 (Box 1)
      - 1940 (Box 1)
      - 1941 (Box 1)
    - Cross and the Flag
      (memos, drafts, and background material)
      - April 1942 (Box 2)
      - May 1942 (Box 2)
      - June 1942 (Box 2)
      - July 1942 (Box 2)
      - August 1942 (Box 2)
      - September 1942 (Box 2)
      - October-November 1942 (Box 2)
      - December 1942 (Box 2)
      - Manuscripts, unsolicited, submitted (Box 2)
    - D (miscellaneous) (Box 2)
    - Day, Stephen A. (Box 2)
    - Defender. See also Gerald B. Winrod (Box 2)
    - Dennis, Lawrence (Box 2)
      (Weekly Foreign Letter)
    - Dilling, Elizabeth (Box 2)
    - Doman, Bernard A. (Box 2)
    - E (miscellaneous) (Box 2)
    - Eaton, Elton R. (Box 2)
    - Election correspondence (Box 2)
    - F (miscellaneous) (Box 2)
    - Fish, Hamilton (Box 2)
    - Foreign Policy Association (Box 2)
    - Form letters (filed as Appeal Letters beginning in 1948)
      - 1939 (Box 2)
      - 1940 (Box 2)
      - 1941 (Box 2)
      - 1942 (Box 2)
    - Forman, Carol (Box 2)
    - G (miscellaneous) (Box 2)
    - Guthrie, Thomas (Box 2)
    - H (miscellaneous) (Box 2)
    - Hoffman, Clare (Box 2)
    - Holt, Rush D. (Box 2)
    - Hoop of Steel: published booklet and drafts (Box 2)
    - Hudson, Charles B. (Box 2)
      ("America in Danger" newsletter)
    - Invitations
      - 1939 (Box 2)
      - 1940-1941 (Box 2)
    - J (miscellaneous) (Box 2)
    - K (miscellaneous) (Box 2)
    - L (miscellaneous) (Box 3)
    - "Lend-Lease" Bill 1776 (Box 3)
    - Lindbergh, Charles (Box 3)
    - Long, Huey, Memorial (Box 3)
    - Louisiana miscellaneous 1939-1940 (Box 3)
    - M (miscellaneous) (Box 3)
    - McCormick, Jane Work (Box 3)
    - MacDougall, Ernest D. (Box 3)
    - Magazine agents (Box 3)
    - Maines, George (Box 3)
    - Manuscript: "The War Mongers" (Box 3)
      (date uncertain)
    - Manuscript: "Witnesses Against War" (Box 3)
    - Manuscript: "Father Coughlin and the Jews" (Box 3)
    - Memoranda
      - circa 1939 (Box 3)
      - 1939 (Box 3)
      - 1940-1941 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Corporation and Securities Commission (Box 3)
    - Michigan Democrat (Box 3)
    - N (miscellaneous) (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings
      - 1939-1942 undated (Box 3)
      - 1939 (Box 3)
      - 1940 (Box 3)
      - 1941 (Box 3)
      - 1942, 3 folders (Box 3)
        (largely re election)
    - Nye, Gerald P. (Box 3)
    - O (miscellaneous) (Box 3)
    - Olympia meetings: financial and shorthand notebook (Box 3)
    - P (miscellaneous) (Box 3)
    - Petitions "to keep America out of Foreign wars," 1939-1940, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Petitions opposing alliance with Russia 1941, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Prentice-Hall, Inc. (Box 4)
    - Press releases 1942 (Box 4)
    - Printer: Arnold Powers, Inc. (Box 4)
    - Prospectuses and memoranda for meetings (Box 4)
    - R (miscellaneous) (Box 4)
    - Radio broadcasts
      (also in oversize folder Ac)
      - Polish radio manuscripts (Jarosz) 1939 (Box 4)
      - Published addresses 1939-1940 (Box 4)
        [Microfilm available in box 98; also available in out-sized folder]
      - Published addresses 1939-1940, 2 folders (Box 4)
        (edited copies and drafts)
      - Undated (Box 4)
      - 1939
        - January 7 (Box 4)
          ("Benefits of Democracy")
        - January 12 (Box 4)
          NY Advertising Club
        - May (Box 4)
        - June (Box 4)
        - July (Box 4)
        - August (Box 4)
        - September (Box 4)
        - October (Box 4)
        - November (Box 4)
        - December (Box 4)
      - 1940
        - January (Box 5)
        - February (Box 5)
        - March (Box 5)
        - April (Box 5)
        - May (Box 5)
        - June (Box 5)
        - July (Box 5)
        - August (Box 5)
        - September (Box 5)
        - October (Box 5)
        - November (Box 5)
        - December (Box 5)
      - 1941
        - Undated (Box 5)
          (include mimeographed addresses)
        - January (Box 5)
        - February (Box 5)
        - March (Box 5)
        - April (Box 5)
        - May (Box 6)
        - June (Box 6)
        - July (Box 6)
        - August (Box 6)
        - September (Box 6)
        - October (Box 6)
        - November (Box 6)
        - December (Box 6)
      - 1942
        - January-February (Box 6)
        - March-June (Box 6)
        - July-August (Box 6)
        - September-October (Box 6)
    - Reynolds, Robert R. (Box 6)
    - Religious (Box 6)
    - S (miscellaneous), 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Short, Dewey (Box 6)
    - Smith, L. Z. (Box 6)
    - Smith family (Box 6)
      (including son)
    - Sokolsky, George (Box 6)
    - Sorenson, Mrs. S. C. (Box 6)
    - Speech memos
      - 1939 (Box 6)